Guide to the Edward Haertel papers SC1257
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Edward Haertel papers
1979-2001
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Haertel, Edward
SC1257
6.75 Linear Feet
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Edward Haertel earned a B.A. in mathematics from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, and a Ph.D. in Education from the University of Chicago. In 1980, Haertel joined the faculty at the Stanford Graduate School of Education as an assistant professor. Since then, he has served as associate professor, Associate Dean for Facutly Affairs, and is now the Jacks Family Professor of Education, Emeritus.
Haertel's research centers on policy uses of achievement test data; the measurement of school learning; statistical issues in testing and accountability systems; and the impact of testing on curriculum and instruction. He has been closely involved in the creation and maintenance of California's school accountability system, and has served on advisory committees for other states and for testing companies.
Haertel has served as president of the National Council on Measurement in Education (1998-99), as a member of the National Assessment Governing Board (1997-2003), and as a member of the joint committee for 1999 edition of the Standards for Educational and Psychological Testing (1994-1999). He was a Fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences (1994-95) and is a Fellow of the American Psychological Association and currently vice president of the National Academy of Education.
Text excerpted from http://web.stanford.edu/~haertel/.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of Haertel's correspondence and memoranda, chronological files, and some teaching files.
Education--Study and teaching (Graduate); Letters.; Haertel, Edward
- Papers, Accession ARCH_2015_113
  - Correspondence and Memos
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1986; 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1984-2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - PSE History (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Haertel - Chron File, 1980 Sept (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Haertel - Chron File, 1981 Jan (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Haertel - Chron File, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Haertel - Chron File, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Assessment Governing Board (NAGB)
    Scope and Contents
    Much of the material relates to Haertel's service on the National Assessment Governing Board (NAGB), which oversees the National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP). There is also material related to his service on the NAEP Technical Review Panel (TRP), which has done many small studies of various issues related to NAEP. Much of the material centers on controversies around NAGB’s procedures for establishing cut scores defining achievement levels (Basic, Proficient, Advanced) on the various NAEP tests. There is also some material dating to Haertel's time as a Fellow of the American Statistical Association and the American Educational Research Association, working at the National Center for Education Statistics (NCES) in Washington, DC on possible redesigns of national education data indicator systems. As part of that work, they collected some documents from earlier redesign discussions.
  - Stanford Graduate School of Education
    Much of this material dates from Haertel's service as Associate Dean for Faculty Affairs, but there’s also documents related to various efforts at defining course sequences and requirements for doctoral training in quantitative research methods. Other folders document deliberations leading to the closure of our counseling psychology program some years ago. Materials also document Haertel's involvement in a controversy over standard setting in the Commonwealth of Kentucky some years ago.
  - California Learning Assessment System (CLAS)
    Includes material on the ill-fated California Learning Assessment System (CLAS), including some actual test materials used in the early 1990s when CLAS was being piloted. TAlso includes material from Haertel's service as director and as president of the National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), material related to the LGBT special interest group of AERA, and a few documents from early in the history of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards.
  - Audiovisual material
    - FCL Collaborative Interview Series, 2000; 2 optical disc(s) (CD)
    - Mellon presentation, 1996-11; 1 optical disc(s) (CD-R)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2015-141
  - California Learning Assessment System (CLAS), undated (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - California Learning Assessment System (CLAS), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME) (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - School's Out (LGBT Group in SUSE), 1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanford University Domestic Partner Benefits, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Out at Stanford (OUTAS) Faculty/Staff LBGT Organization, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA) General Council, 1995-12-10 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA) Ethical Studies, 2000-1-11 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago Department of Education, 1997-9-17 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Testing Futures, National Academy of Education, 1989-8-30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA) Special Interest Group (SIG), 1991-4-15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA) Special Interest Group (SIG), 1991-8-23 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA) Special Interest Group (SIG), 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Counseling Psychology Program, 2005-6-24 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Child Psychology Program, 2005-6-21 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Honig Rebuttal, 1984-6-24 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - External Review of the School of Education, 1995-11-6 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stanford University School of Education (SUSE) Billet Deliberations, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Haertel, 2001-9-21 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Quantitative Research Ed Haertel, 2003-3-7 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Quantitative Training Subcommittee, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Snow Quanitative Methods Sequence Committee, 2005-6-18 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Desig. Insta. Appointments, 2005-6-27 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Search Committee Resources, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - International Post Sec, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Search Steering Committee Process Interviews, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - June Retreats, 2010-5-27 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Stanford University School of Education (SUSE), 2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stanford University School of Education (SUSE) Policy, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Undergrad Honors Program, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Undergrad Minor, 2008-5-1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University School of Education Academic Programs, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stanford University School of Education Structure, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - RTG, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Guidelines for Stanford School of Education (SUSE) Academic Advising, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Distributed Minors, 1996-5-15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Stanford and the Schools, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Stanford Univeristy School of Education (SUSE)/ Graduate School of Education (GSE) Faculty Search Procedures, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - PSE Meetings, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - National Technical Advisory Committee Meeting, 1995-9-1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Kentucky Instructional Results Information System (KIRIS) standard setting controversy, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - NAGB Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Education Booklets, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Volunteer National Tests (VNTs), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Loose papers, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Stufflebean Evaluation of NAGA, 1991-8-1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME) to TRP Reports, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Background and Followup to Chapter 5 of Grading the Nation's Report Card, 1999-3-1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Expert Feedback "Setting Goals for the National Assessment for Educational Progress (NAEP)", 1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - National Assessment Governing Board Policy Statements, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - National Assessment Governing Board Redesign, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Assessment related publications, undated (Box 11)
  - CA Assessment program "Beyond the bubble" telecast, 1989-10; 12.1; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 12)
  - Examining the President's Annual testing agenda: Challenges for the Educational Community Tape 1, undated; 12.2; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 12)
  - Examining the President's Annual testing agenda: Challenges for the Educational Community Tape 2, undated; 12.3; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 12)
  - Youth Radio-Standardized test boycotts - NPR, 2001-5-30; 12.4; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 12)
  - FCL Collaborative Interview Series CD Set. Learning Technology Center. Peabody College at Vanderbilt University - DISC 1, 2000; 12.5; 1 compact disc(s) (Box 12)
  - FCL Collaborative Interview Series CD Set. Learning Technology Center. Peabody College at Vanderbilt University - DISC 2, 2000; 12.6; 1 compact disc(s) (Box 12)
  - Mellon, 1996-11; 12.7; 1 compact disc(s) (Box 12)